Okay, so let's talk about
some of the classifications
of risks that you need to
be aware of for the exam.
Now, two basic classifications here,
there's something called the effect-based
risk and something called the source-based
risk.
So the effect-based
risk is basically inherent
in the project, inherent
in the endeavor, right?
So all of your constraints, for example,
everything within the project,
right, your scope, your schedule, they
could all identify risks on a project.
As you're developing your schedule,
you're going to be identifying risk.
As you're figuring out the budget for your
project, you're going
to be identifying risk.
As you're trying to identify the resources
on your project, you're identifying risk.
As you're collecting requirements
and coming up with the
scope of the project,
again, you're identifying risk.
So it's always, it's inherent already
there.
So it's always there on your project.
The main thing is to identify them.
So that is something called the
effect-based risk, right?
It's always inherent there.
Then you have something
called the source-based risk, and
source-based risk then is
basically refers to the origin.
Where did that risk come from?
There could be internal
factors, internal to
the organization, internal to the project.
There could be external factors,
such as, for example, vendor delaying
shipment of raw materials, many risks are
going to be external, right?
So raw materials, exchange rates,
and so and so forth, right?
These can all be risk to your project.
You have trade union workers, again,
that you could identify that as a risk on
your project as well, right, potential for
them going on strike, as a simple example.
So you've got external factors internal
within your organization, right?
You've got technical risks,
industry-specific risks.
There's many, many different different
types of risks.
So the source-based risk then refers to
the actual origin.
Where does they actually come from?
And in fact, internal, internal to the
organization.
Perfect example here.
A failure of one team can impact another
team.
So internal to your project in this case,
one team fails.
That could lead to the failure of another
team.
Think of business partners, for example.
One business partner fails.
that could bring down the entire
partnership.
Now, additional classifications of risks.
So something called a business risk and
something called an insurable risk.
And a business risk is, again,
an uncertainty that is, again,
inherent in the business.
It's already inherent in the actual
business venture itself.
As we're doing this
project, there's no guarantee
that this project is
going to be a success.
And in fact, this then goes back to,
well, what does success mean on a project?
Just being on budget
and on schedule doesn't
necessarily mean that
the project is a success.
You could be on budget and on schedule,
but the entire business venture may fail.
You may fail to make enough sales,
and you've lost all that money,
the whole business collapses.
Even though you're
within schedule and within
budget, but was that a successful project?
No.
So business risk then is always inherent
in the actual business itself.
So again, this project, even though it may
be within schedule and within budget,
it might not be a successful project.
Or rather, it might not end up being a
successful venture.
And this is, like I said, inherent, but
it's not something you can insure against.
It's not insurable.
So they have a business risk and you have
an insurable risk.
An insurable risk then, obviously,
is something that you can insure against,
such as fire, theft and, you know,
just the typical insurance, the types of
insurance that you buy, say, for your home
or for your car, right?
You have insurance for your business as
well.
Now, let's talk about some of the business,
some of the common business risks.
right, and these four are really just some
of the real common business type risks.
So competition.
So your competitor has a feature that you
don't have, right?
That's a risk to you.
That's a risk to your project.
So you're building this product, but
your competitor has a superior product.
Or even there's now increased competition
in the marketplace.
When you started off, you were the only
one, or there were only a few players out
there, There's only few competitors out
there.
Now it's just being saturated with
competitors.
Again, that can be a risk to your
organization.
That could be a risk to your project.
Legislation as well.
Compliance is standard.
Compliance to regulations.
New law suddenly gets
enacted and you might end
up having to extend the
timeline for your project.
We need to implement this new law.
That's a very simple system back in my HR
days.
There would always be new HIPAA laws
coming in or tax law.
that would impact payroll and so and so
forth.
So now we're either that could create a
new project or if we're in the middle of a
project now we need to add in these
additional items to this project.
That can extend the timeline on the
project.
But these are again, these are all risks
on your project, all uncertainties.
Monetary as well, I
mean that's obviously the
biggest risk on your
project, right, money, right?
So exchange rates, raw materials,
price of raw materials suddenly increases.
There's not much you can do about that.
And again, you can't
always identify, but if
you can identify it, we
want to identify them.
We want to identify, oh, there might be a
fluctuation in raw material prices,
just because of what we've been hearing on
the news or anything else.
So operational risk then would be things
like theft, fraud, injury.
So these again are all risks on your
project, right?
So again, something you want to identify.
So remember, risk is an uncertainty,
right?
But we want to try and prevent a negative
risk from a current.
A positive risk, obviously we want to
embrace it.
It's a negative risk we want to try to
identify it early.
You know, we have something, or rather we
have a plan to deal with it.
Now, risks exist at two levels.
You have something called individual risks
and something called
overall project risks.
Individual risks, right, basically are
risks that just affect one, you know,
it's really one objective, affects one
team, affects one activity, right,
affects one requirement or it affects one
area, just one objective at some kind,
whereas overall
project risks refers to risk
that impact the entire project as a whole.
Now, how do we actually deal with these as
we're talking about all of the analysis?
right, the risk analysis process,
where we're going to be talking about
qualitative analysis and quantitative
analysis and risk response strategies.
Well, there's no difference between the
individual and overall project risk when
it comes to analysis, right, and how to
respond to the risk.
Everything that we are going to be
covering in risk management, like refers
to both individual risks as well as
overall project risks.
And then just as a side note, there's
another type of classification of risk,
if you like, something called the
non-event risk.
And a non-event risk really is just
something that can happen.
You don't really have much control over
it.
So as a very simple example, you know,
a perfect example here.
Customer changed their mind.
They changed their mind about functionality
or change their mind about a product.
Well, nothing actually triggered them.
They just happened to change their mind.
and that's it.
They change their mind, project is over.
So there's nothing that triggered it.
So that is something known as a non-event
risk.
So these are just some of the different
classifications of risks and some
classifications of risks that you need to
be aware of for the P&P exam.